When we think about alien civilizations
知的生命体の文明について考えるとき
we tend to look into the vastness of space, to far away planets.
広大な宇宙や遠い惑星に
目を向けがちだ
But there is another incredibly vast dimension that we might be giving too little thought to:
だが、驚くほど広大なもう一つの次元には
ほとんど考えが及んでいない
time
時間だ
Could it be that over the last hundreds of millions of years, other civilizations existed on earth?
過去数億年にわたり
地球に別の文明が存在していたのでは？
Indigenous technological species that rose and died out?
土着の、技術を持つ種が台頭し
そして滅んだのでは？
And that they or their artifacts are buried beneath our feet?
その種と、それらの遺物が
私たちの足元に埋まっているのでは？
What does science have to say about this and what are the implications for us?
この疑問に科学はどう答えるだろう？
そして、私たちに何を示唆するだろう？
Life on earth has existed for 4 billion years,
地球上の生命は
40億年前から存在し
mostly as single celled organisms until some 540 million years ago
5.4億年前までは
ほぼ単細胞生物だった
the Cambrian explosion heralded the age of animals.
カンブリア爆発で動物の時代になるまでは
A huge time window for our indigenous aliens.
土着の知的生命体にとって
巨大な猶予が存在する
Where would we look for them and what could we hope to find?
どこを探せば見つかるか
そして何を見ることになるのか？
Sadly we have only one civilization to look at:
残念ながら、参照できる文明はたった一つで
Ourselves.
人類自身のものだ
Anatomically modern humans emerged around 300,000 years ago
解剖学的にみて現生人類の出現は
約30万年前で
and probably lived in small groups of hunter gatherers, slowly spreading around the world.
おそらく狩猟採集の小集団で生活し
緩やかに世界に広がっていった
Progress was slow and our lifestyle did not change much, although there may have been local bursts of complexity.
進歩は遅く、生活様式の変化も乏しかったが
局所的な高度化はあったかも
Until about 10,000 years ago, when the agricultural revolution changed our lifestyle forever,
約1万年前、農業革命が
私たちの生活様式を一変させ
enabling massive population growth and technological progress.
大規模な人口増加と
技術的進歩が可能となった
Rather than just animals with culture and tools that would have been invisible from space,  we changed the face of the planet,
単なる「文化や道具をもった動物」でなく
宇宙から見た地球の外見まで変えてみせた
cleared forests and constructed cities and temples for our gods at breathtaking speeds and scales.
驚異的な速さとスケールで
森林を切り拓き、都市と神殿をつくりあげたのだ
Until about 300 years ago, we became an industrial species
300年ほど前
私たちは工業を営む種となった
Until about 300 years ago, we became an industrial species
またもや人口が飛躍的に増加し
地球への影響も大きくなった
We could say that our 300,000 year long history has three phases:
人類30万年の歴史は
3段階に分けられるだろう
We were hunter gatherers for 97%, farmers for 2.9%
97％は狩猟採集民として
2.9％は農耕民として
and industrialists for 0.1% of our history.
そして0.1％が工業民だが
And yet we are super new on earth.
そもそも人類自体が
地球では新顔だ
On geological timescales, even the sturdiest things lose their durability.
地質学的なタイムスケールでは
最も頑丈な物質さえ永続性を失う
The oldest large scale surface is in the Negev Desert, a meager 1.8 million years old.
地表に最も長く存続しているのはネゲヴ砂漠で
180万年に過ぎない
Everything older has been crushed to dust or turned over and it is either below the ground, or covered by ice or ocean.
より古いものは粉砕されたり分解されたりで
地下にあるか、氷や海に覆われている
Our age, the Anthropocene will be a layer only a few centimeters thick in a few million years.
私たちの時代、人新世は数百万年後には
たった数cmの地層となるだろう
If there were aliens before us and they too went through these three phases, what would remain of them?
人類以前に知的生命体が存在し
この3段階を経たなら何が残るだろう
What can we learn about indegnous aliens by looking at ourselves?
未知の知的生命体について
人類自身から何が示唆されるだろう
Hunter & Gatherer Aliens
狩猟採集型の知的生命体
We actually know that in the last few million years, there were hunter gatherers aliens.
ここ数百万年の間に
狩猟採集型の知的生命体は実在した
Our ancestors like Homo Erectus and cousins like the Neanderthals or Denisovans
私たちの祖先、ホモ・エレクトスや
近縁のネアンデルタール人やデニソワ人
and probably many more that we haven’t found yet or are lost to time forever.
そして他にも未発見・発見不能の存在が
おそらく多数いたのだ
They left fragments of their bodies, of weapons and tools and even art.
彼らは肉体の一部、武器や道具
あるいは芸術さえも残した
Considering how long they existed and how little remains of them although they lived not that far from our present
わりと近年まで、長く存続したのに
彼らの痕跡が少ないことを考慮すると
it is ​easy to think there have been others
他の存在も容易に想像できる
Intelligent animals like us that could talk and use tools and fire, that had culture and art.
私たちのような、言葉を話し、道具や火を扱い
文化や芸術を持つ知的な動物
For the last two million years, most hominins lived as hunter-gatherers –
この200万年
ほとんどのヒト科は狩猟採集民だった
so if these aliens never moved up higher on the tech tree,
もし、次の技術段階に移行しないなら
hundreds of different species and cultures could have existed without leaving any traces.
何百もの異なる種や文化が
痕跡を残さずに存在し得たのだ
Their artifacts lost to biological and then geological processes.
彼らの遺物は生物学的
そして地質学的プロセスにより失われたのだ
At worst they would leave absolutely nothing to be found after thousands of years.
最悪の場合
数千年で痕跡が完全に消失する
But what about fossils?
だが化石は？
We talked about how unlikely the process of fossilization is in more detail in our dinosaur video,
化石化の望みの薄さは
恐竜の動画で詳細に扱ったが
but in a nutshell, per hundred thousand years of earth's history we only get a handful of good fossils.
ザックリいうと、良質な化石は
10万年で一握り程度しか得られないのだ
So we might easily just miss fossils of such people
だから存在を見失い得るし
– but even if we had any, we would not necessarily be able to identify them as hunter gatherers.
化石を見つけても
狩猟採集民と特定できるとは限らない
Agricultural and Empire Aliens
農耕と帝国の知的生命体
Looking at humans again, agricultural societies left much more to be dug up and found,
人類に再び着目すると
農耕社会では発掘可能な痕跡が多く残される
because they used more sophisticated tools made from sturdier materials and had to feed millions, leaving many more artifacts.
彼らはより頑丈で洗練された道具を用い
何百万人も養ったため、多くの遺物を残したのだ
Farming allowed them to specialize and develop tech from writing to navigation, architecture and government.
農耕は専門分化を可能とし
文字、航海術、農耕、政治の技術を発展させた
Over thousands of years city states became kingdoms and empires,
何千年もかけ
都市国家は王国や帝国になり
some existing for millennia before they fell.
滅びるまでに
数千年も存続したものもある
Many of the buildings or monuments they constructed are still around
その建造物やモニュメントの多くは今も残り
and traces of them will exist for a few thousand more years.
その痕跡は数千年は存続するだろう
Some only as outlines in the ground, but still recognizable to future archaeologists.
一部は輪郭だけになるが
未来の考古学者にはわかるだろう
The pyramids are piles of limestone so massive that they will probably be around for hundreds of thousands of years.
ピラミッドは石灰岩の山であり
その巨大さから何十万年も存続しそうだ
And because of the greater numbers of humans that lived during our farm and empire period,
また、より多くの人口が
農耕時代や帝国時代を生きたため
we can expect way more fossils and artifacts to be detectable, maybe for a few million years before they vanish.
はるかに多くの化石や遺物が残るだろうし
消滅までに数百万年を要するかも
So we can say with confidence that no such indigenous alien civilization existed in the last few million years
だから、ここ数百万年では
土着の知的生命体による文明はなかったと断言できる
because otherwise we would have found something that they left.
存在したなら
痕跡が当然みつかるからだ
This still leaves a window of hundreds of millions of years,
それでも、数億年の期間が候補として残る
back to the emergence of complex life, where we would not be able to tell.
複雑な生命の誕生時点までさかのぼるなら
知りえないのだ
If there were alien pre industrial societies and empires on the level of the ancient Romans or Chinese,
もし古代のローマや中国レベルの前工業社会と帝国を
知的生命体が築いても
they would have likely disappeared without a trace.
跡形もなく消えているだろう
Their tools, even advanced metals, would have rotted away
彼らの道具は、高度な金属でさえ
朽ち果てているはずだ
If they dug up canals, cleared forests and built cities,
運河を掘り、森林を拓き
都市を築いたとしても
their traces would be very hard to distinguish from nature.
その痕跡はもはや
自然物と見分けがつかない
Maybe there once was an empire of cephalopods occupying impressive cities in swamps and lakes,
沼や池で素晴らしい都市を築いた
頭足類の帝国があったかも
made from wood and stone.
建材は木と石だ
Their engineers flooding land to build wet cities, their poets reciting poems in a language of colors.
エンジニアは浸水により湿った都市を築き
詩人は色を言語として詩を詠んだ
Maybe they never industrialized
おそらく工業化には至らず
– maybe their society was too stable or not inventive enough or they never got a chance.
原因は社会の安定感か、不十分な発明性か
単に機会に恵まれなかったのかも
A single event like an asteroid, an epidemic or an ice age could just have deleted their civilization,
そして小惑星や疫病、氷河期といった
単発の出来事でも文明は消滅し
ground up their temples as their soft bodies rotted away.
柔らかな身体は朽ち果て
寺院もすり潰されうる
Sadly we don’t have the tiniest amount of evidence for any such civilization.
だが残念ながら、そのような文明について
かすかな証拠すらない
After a few million years at best, their achievements would have dissolved into nothing.
せいぜい数百万年後には
彼らの実績は無に帰してしまうだろう
Industrial Indigenous Aliens
工業的な土着の知的生命体
What about industrial civilizations, like humanity today?
現在の人類のような
工業文明はどうだろう
Imagine humans died out suddenly, through a pandemic or cosmic rays or something like that.
パンデミックや宇宙線などで
人類が突如として滅亡した場合を想像しよう
What would remain?
何が残るだろう
Our impact on the planet is orders of magnitude greater than that of our ancestors.
私たちが地球に与える影響は
祖先よりも桁外れに大きい
The fossil record will show a great extinction of wildlife
化石記録から、野生動物の大絶滅と
and an explosion of fossils from human associated animals, like rats, cows, pigs and chickens.
ラット、牛、豚、鶏といった
人類に関わる動物化石の爆発的な増加がわかるだろう
Like the structures of our ancestors,
祖先の建造物と同様
skyscrapers and streets and harddrives will basically crumble into nothingness in a few millennia.
高層ビルや道路、ハードディスクは
基本的に数千年で崩れ、無に帰すだろう
But because there were so many humans everywhere,
だが人間はどこにでも多数いたので
唐突な絶滅から数百万年は
人類の存在を示唆するものがあるはずだ
The byproducts of our industrial lifestyle might actually give us away for some hundreds of millions of gas.
私たちの工業的なライフスタイルの副産物は
数億年にわたり痕跡を残すかもしれない
We use massive amounts of artificial fertilizer
私たちが利用する大量の化学肥料は
which redirects earth’s flow of nitrogen that is being deposited in the soil.
地球の窒素循環の流れを変え
土壌に蓄積させていく
Mining metals and rare Earth elements leaves long term scars and depletes natural resources.
金属やレアアースの採掘は長期の傷跡を残し
天然資源を枯渇させる
We saturate our oceans with plastics that find their way to the ocean floor
海をプラスチックで満たし
それが海底に到達すると
and may persist for hundreds of millions of years.
数億年にわたり残留しうる
There are radioactive elements and their decay,
放射性元素とその崩壊について
unnatural accumulations of elements that do not exist outside labs or weapons.
研究所や兵器以外ではありえない
不自然な集積がある
And of course, in our short industrial history
そしてもちろん
短い産業史のなかで
we have changed the proportion of CO2 in the air by burning massive amounts of fossil fuels,
私たちは大量の化石燃料を燃やして
大気中のCO2濃度を変え
increasing the acidity of the oceans and so on.
海の酸性度を高めたりしてきた
We may already have left a mark in the geological record.
すでに地質学的な記録に
痕跡を残しているのかもしれない
So far we have found no traces of an industrial alien civilization.
今のところ、知的生命体による
産業文明の痕跡は見つかっていない
No layers of weird chemicals or displaced elements.
奇妙な化学物質の層や
元素が収集された層もない
No radioactive layer to indicate that once great nations waged nuclear war.
大国による核戦争を示唆するような
放射性物質の層もない
We do see mass extinctions and massive shifts in the fossil records
化石記録から大量絶滅や
大規模移動が示唆されるが
but no evidence that they did not occur naturally.
その自然発生を否定する材料はない
And ironically we’ve hit upon an interesting problem here:
皮肉なことに
ここで興味深い問題に直面した
If industrial societies stress the ecosystem enough to cause their own extinction,
もし産業社会が、自滅を招くほど
生態系に負荷をかけるなら
they won’t be around that long.
長くは続かないだろうが
But if they become sustainable their imprint on the geological record may be tiny.
もし持続可能な社会になれば
地質学的記録への痕跡はごく小さいかも
If past industrial civilizations were sustainable before they died out,
過去の産業文明が
持続可能だったなら
we may have little to no chance of ever knowing about them.
彼らを知るチャンスは
ほとんど無いかもしれない
In any case, over hundreds of millions of years
いずれにせよ、数億年を経て
these signatures may become very subtle and get overlooked or interpreted as natural.
これらの痕跡はごく微妙なものとなり
見過ごされたり、自然の範囲内と解釈されうる
Even if an industrialized alien society existed 200 million years ago
仮に知的生命体の社会が2億年前に工業化し
and lasted for 100,000 years, 300 times longer than industrial humanity,
人類の300倍にあたる
10万年を存続したとして
it still might be easy to miss it in the geological record.
彼らの地質学的記録は
容易に見落されるかもしれない
In any case, all of this is speculation.
いずれにせよ、全ては憶測だ
In the end we should not use our imagination to trick ourselves into thinking we know anything about our blind spots.
「本来は知りえないことを知っている」
と過信するために想像力を使うべきではない
Just assuming a thing happened because we don’t have evidence against it is a trap we should avoid.
「存在を否定的する証拠が無い＝存在した」
という思い込みは避けるべき罠だ
So for now, if we look at the vastness of time
現時点で
時間軸の広大さを見つめると
it seems as devoid of aliens as the vastness of space.
広大な宇宙空間に触れた時と同様に
知的生命体の不在を感じる
Maybe we are alone in this universe and always were.
私たちは今も昔も
宇宙に孤立しているのかもしれない
Maybe we’ll find traces of others eventually, we don’t know.
いつか何者かの痕跡を見つけるかも、知らんけど
But there is one important takeaway:
一つ重要なポイントがある
The continuation of our civilization is not guaranteed
私たちの文明の存続は保証されておらず
and if we're not careful, we may disappear forever.
慎重さに欠ければ
永遠に消失するかもしれない
Let’s hope that in a few million years, there won't be another civilization studying our layer in the fossil record.
数百万年後、私たちの層の化石記録を研究する
他の文明がないことを期待したい
It’s frustrating to know there are so many things in our past we can’t access.
知りえない過去が多数あると知るのは
もどかしいことです
At least you can avoid that annoying feeling when it comes to other stuff you are interested in, like your favorite TV shows or movies.
少なくとも、好きなTV番組や映画など
興味あるものでは、このイライラを回避できます
You can make this possible by going to NordVPN.com/kurzgesagt.
NordVPN.com/kurzgesagt
にアクセスすればいいのです
NordVPNs service lets you change your virtual location by choosing from over 5200 fast servers in 60 countries all over the world
NordVPNのサービスでは世界60ヵ国にある
5200以上の高速サーバーから、仮想の位置情報を選択でき
and access regionally blocked content or games that may not be available in your country.
地域でブロックされている
コンテンツやゲームにアクセスできます
Secure your internet traffic with top-tier NordVPN encryption, no matter if you’re using a Computer, Tablet or Smartphone.
端末の種類を問わず、最高レベルのNordVPN暗号化で
あなたのインターネットトラフィックを保護します
It’s compatible with every major platform and can be used on 6 devices at once.
主要な全てのプラットフォームに対応しており
一度に6台まで使用可能です
If you want to make the rest of your digital life airtight as well,
他のデジタルライフも
堅牢にしたいなら
NordVPN also offers the secure Password manager NordPass and encrypted cloud storage NordLocker.
安全なパスワードマネージャーであるNordPassと
暗号化クラウドストレージのNordLockerも提供しています
To explore all the games and shows you can get your hands on, go to NordVPN.com/kurzgesagt for an exclusive deal for our viewers.
全てのゲームと番組を入手したいなら
NordVPN.com/kurzgesagtで視聴者独占契約をどうぞ
It’s risk free with NordVPN’s 30 day money back guarantee.
NordVPNの30日間返金保証があるので
リスクはありません
GET INSPIRED BY SCIENCE
-科学からインスピレーションを受け-
LEARN ABOUT THE HISTORY OF LIFE
-生命の歴史を学び-
＆ DREAM OF UTOPIAN CIVILIZATIONS
-理想の文明を思い描く-